A Guide to the Virginia. Secretary of the Commonwealth. Papers relevant to the Floyd Allen case, 1912-1922
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia. Secretary of the Commonwealth. Papers relevant to the Floyd Allen case, 1912-1922
The Library of Virginia
21690, 39265
4.95 cu. ft. (11 boxes)
Virginia. Secretary of the Commonwealth.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred on 12 March 1940 by the Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth, Richmond, Virginia, 23219 [Accession 21690].
Transferred on 4 March 2002 by Unknown [Accession 39265].
Biographical Information
On March 13, 1912, Floyd Allen went on trial in the Carroll County Circuit Court charged with interfering with two deputies in the performance of their duties as they arrested two of his nephews for fighting and disturbing a religious meeting. The next morning the jury delivered a verdict of guilty and Allen was sentenced to one year at the State Penitentiary. Shortly thereafter shooting began in the courtroom and four people were killed, including Judge Thornton L. Massie, Sherriff Lewis F. Webb, the Commonwealth's Attorney William M. Foster, and one spectator, Bettie Ayers. The Allen family claimed that court officials were the first to open fire, while other witnesses contended that Claude Allen, the defendant's son, began the shooting. Nevertheless, Floyd Allen, Claude Swanson Allen, and other members of the Allen family were tried for murder. Floyd Allen was recaptured and in May 1912, found guilty of murder. Claude S. Allen, son of Floyd Allen, had the first of three trials on May 20, 1912. He was also judged guilty of murder in the first degree. Other involved individuals were also brought to trial and received varying sentences. Floyd and Claude S. Allen, despite extensive efforts to have Governor Mann extend clemency, were electrocuted on March 28, 1913.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1912-1922, including clippings, correspondence, drawings, mass mailings, and petitions relating to the "Hillsville" murders
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Contents List
- Affidavits for payment of guards, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Clippings, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1912 March 14-19 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1912 March 20-30 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, Baldwin-Felts Detectives, Inc., 1912 March-June (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, Baldwin-Felts Detectives, Inc., 1912 July-1913 January (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, Baldwin-Felts Detectives, Inc., Wanted posters, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1912 April (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1912 May-June (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1912 July-October (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1912 November 1-15 (Box 2)
- Correspondence, 1912 November 16-18 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1912 November 19 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1912 November 20-24 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1912 November 25-26 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1912 November 26-27 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1912 November 27-30 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1912 December 1-4 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1912 December 5-9 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1912 December 10-19 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1912 December 20-30 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1912 December 31 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, Members of the Virginia General Assembly, 1912-1913 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, Telegrams, 1912-1913 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1913 January 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1913 January 16-25 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1913 January 26-31 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1913 February 1-9 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1913 February 10-26 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1913 March (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Correspondence (undated), ca. 1913-1914 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1914-1917 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1918-1919 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1922 January-March (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1922 April 1-15 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1922 April 17-30 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1922 May 1-12 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1922 May 13-June 1 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1922 June 2-29 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1922 July-August (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1922 September (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1922 October (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Drawings of Carroll County Courtroom, ca. 1912-1913 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Governor Mann, Memorandum regarding applications for clemency, 1912 November (Box 6, Folder 3a)
- Governor Mann, Statement, ca. 1912-1913 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Governor Mann, Typed conservation, 1913 March 27 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Judge Staples, Remarks in sentencing, ca. 1912-1913 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- List of names, A-F, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
- List of names, G-Z, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Mass mailings, 1922 (Box 6, Folder 9-10)
- Mass mailings, 1922 (Box 7, Folder 1-6)
- Notes, 1913 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Petitions, 1912-1913 (Box 8, Folder 2-5)
- Petitions, Transcriptions, 1912 (Box 8, Folder 6-7)
- Petitions, 1922 (Box 9, Folder 1-6)
- Petitions, 1922 (Box 10, Folder 1-6)
- (Box 11, Folder 1)
- (Box 11, Folder 1)
- (Box 11, Folder 3)
- (Box 11, Folder 4)
- (Box 11, Folder 5)
- (Box 11, Folder 6)
- (Box 11, Folder 7)
- (Box 11, Folder 8)
- (Box 11, Folder 9)
- (Box 11, Folder 10)
- (Box 11, Folder 11)
- (Box 11, Folder 12)